<?xml version="1.0"?>
<Project>
  <ProjectTitle>PubMed Central (free) Journal subscriber access Comments? CTN-0020 Primary Outcomes Randomized Multi-site Trial of the Job Seekers' Workshop in Patients with Substance Use Disorders. Drug and Alcohol Dependence 2012;120(1-3):55-64. [doi: 10.1016/j.drugalcdep.2011.06.024] Dace S. Svikis, PhD (Virginia Commonwealth University, MA Node), Lori Keyser-Marcus, PhD (Virginia Commonwealth University, MA Node), Maxine L. Stitzer, PhD (Johns Hopkins University School of Medicine), Traci R. Rieckmann, PhD (Oregon Health Science University, WS Node), Lauretta Safford, MSW (Virginia Commonwealth University, MA Node), Peter Loeb (Allen and Loeb Associates, San Francisco), Tim Allen (Allen and Loeb Associates, San Francisco), Carol Luna-Anderson, PhD (The Life Link, SW Node), Sudie E. Back, PhD (Medical University of South Carolina, SC Node), Judith Cohen, PhD (East Bay Community Recovery Project, WS Node), Michael A. DeBernardi, PsyD (The Life Link, SW Node), Bruce Dillard (Medical University of South Carolina, SC Node), Alyssa A. Forcehimes, PhD (University of New Mexico, SW Node), William B. Jaffee, PhD (McLean Hospital, NEC Node), Therese Killeen, PhD, APRN (Medical University of South Carolina, SC Node), Ken B. Kolodner (Epidemiology and Statistical Consulting, Baltimore, MD), Michael S. Levy, PhD (CAB Health and Recovery Services, NEC Node), Diane Pallas, PsyD (Na'Nizhoozhi Center, Inc., SW Node), Harold I. Perl, PhD (Center for the Clinical Trials Network, NIDA), Jennifer Sharpe Potter, PhD, MPH (University of Texas Health Science Center, NEC Node), Scott E. Provost, MSW, MM (McLean Hospital, NEC Node), Karen Reese, MA, CAC-AD (Man Alive, Inc., MA Node), Royce Sampson, MSN, APRN-BC (Medical University of South Carolina, SC Node), Allison Sepulveda (Virginia Commonwealth University, MA Node), Ned Snead (Chesterfield Community Services Board, MA Node), Conrad J. Wong, PhD (Eli Lily and Company, Greenwood, IN), Joan E. Zweben, PhD (East Bay Community Recovery Project, WS Node). This is the Primary Outcomes Paper for CTN-0020. Unemployment is associated with negative outcomes both during and after drug abuse treatment. Interventions designed to increase rates of employment may also improve drug abuse treatment outcomes. The purpose of this multi-site clinical trial, protocol CTN-0020, was to evaluate the Job Seekers' Workshop (JSW), a three-session, manualized program designed to train patients in the skills needed to find and secure a job. Study participants were recruited through the National Drug Abuse Treatment Clinical Trials Network (CTN) from six psychosocial counseling (n=327) and five methadone maintenance (n=301) drug treatment programs. Participants were randomly assigned to either standard care (program-specific services plus brochure with local employment resources) (SC) or standard care plus JSW. Three 4-h small group JSW sessions were offered weekly by trained JSW facilitators with ongoing fidelity monitoring. JSW and SC participants had similar 12- and 24-week results for the primary outcome measure (i.e., obtaining a new taxed job or enrollment in a training program). Specifically, one-fifth of participants at 12 weeks (20.1-24.3%) and nearly one-third at 24 weeks (31.4-31.9%) had positive outcomes, with "obtaining a new taxed job" accounting for the majority of cases. Conclusions: Job Seekers' Workshop group participants did not have higher rates of employment/training than standard care controls. Rates of job acquisition were modest for both groups, suggesting more intensive interventions may be needed. Alternate targets (e.g., enhancing patient motivation, training in job-specific skills) warrant further study as well. Secondary analyses of present study findings will examine potential mediators and moderators of study outcomes, with a focus on barriers to employment and other variables. (Article (Peer-Reviewed), PDF, English, 2012) Keywords: Community health services | CTN primary outcomes | Job Seekers Workshop | Skills building | Vocational rehabilitation | Drug and Alcohol Dependence (journal) Document No: 713, PMID: 21643458, PMCID: PMC3107016. Submitted by the CTN Dissemination Librarians, 8/1/2011. AUTHORS LINK Allen, Tim Back, Sudie E. Cohen, Judith DeBernardi, Michael A. Dillard, Bruce Forcehimes, Alyssa A. Jaffee, William B. Keyser-Marcus, Lori Killeen, Therese Kolodner, Ken B. Levy, Michael S. Loeb, Peter Luna-Anderson, Carol Pallas, Diane Perl, Harold I. Potter, Jennifer Sharpe Provost, Scott E. Reese, Karen Rieckmann, Traci R. Safford, Lauretta Sampson, Royce Sepulveda, Allison Snead, Ned Stitzer, Maxine L. Svikis, Dace S. Wong, Conrad J. Zweben, Joan E. PROTOCOLS NIDA-CTN-0020 PARTICIPATING NODES LINK Mid-Atlantic Great Lakes Regional New England Consortium Southern Consortium Southwest Western States Supported by a grant from the National Institute on Drug Abuse to the University of Washington Alcohol and Drug Abuse Institute. The materials on this site have neither been created nor reviewed by NIDA. Updated 6/2012 -- http://ctndisseminationlibrary.org/display/713.htm info@ctndisseminationlibrary.org</ProjectTitle>
  <CitationSet>
    <Citation>Comments?</Citation>
  </CitationSet>
  <AuthorSet>
    <Name>CTN-0020 Primary Outcomes</Name>
    <DegreeSet/>
    <AffiliationSet>
      <Affiliation/>
    </AffiliationSet>
  </AuthorSet>
  <ProjectDescription>
    <Abstract>
      <AbstractText>Randomized Multi-site Trial of the Job Seekers' Workshop in Patients with Substance Use Disorders.</AbstractText>
      <PopulationSpecification>
        <Enrollment>
          <CriterionSet>
            <Criterion>
              <CriterionType>placeholder</CriterionType>
              <CriterionSpecification>placeholder</CriterionSpecification>
            </Criterion>
          </CriterionSet>
        </Enrollment>
        <Allocation>
          <AllocationPredicate>
            <AllocationPredicateFunction>
              <AllocationPredicateFunctionSignature>placeholder</AllocationPredicateFunctionSignature>
              <AllocationPredicateFunctionArgumentSet>
                <AllocationPredicateFunctionArgument>
                  <AllocationPredicateFunctionArgumentName>placeholder</AllocationPredicateFunctionArgumentName>
                  <AllocationPredicateFunctionArgumentValue>placeholder</AllocationPredicateFunctionArgumentValue>
                </AllocationPredicateFunctionArgument>
              </AllocationPredicateFunctionArgumentSet>
            </AllocationPredicateFunction>
          </AllocationPredicate>
        </Allocation>
        <AllocatedStudyArmSet>
          <AllocatedStudyArm>
            <Name>placeholder</Name>
            <InitialSize>
              <SubgroupSet>
                <Subgroup>
                  <Name>placeholder</Name>
                  <Size>placeholder</Size>
                </Subgroup>
              </SubgroupSet>
            </InitialSize>
            <InterventionSet>
              <Intervention>placeholder</Intervention>
            </InterventionSet>
            <MetricResultSet>
              <MetricResult/>
            </MetricResultSet>
          </AllocatedStudyArm>
        </AllocatedStudyArmSet>
        <PlannedActionSet>
          <PlannedAction>
            <Name>placeholder</Name>
            <IntendedTargetPopulation>placeholder</IntendedTargetPopulation>
            <PlannedActionSpecification>
              <TypeOfAction>placeholder</TypeOfAction>
              <TypeSpecificFields/>
            </PlannedActionSpecification>
          </PlannedAction>
        </PlannedActionSet>
        <MetricSpecificationSet>
          <MetricSpecification>
            <Name>placeholder</Name>
            <Measurement>
              <MeasurementName>placeholder</MeasurementName>
              <MeasurementUnits>placeholder</MeasurementUnits>
            </Measurement>
            <IntendedTargetPopulationSet>
              <IntendedTargetPopulation>
                <Name>placeholder</Name>
                <Value>placeholder</Value>
              </IntendedTargetPopulation>
            </IntendedTargetPopulationSet>
            <StatisticSpecification>
              <StatisticName>placeholder</StatisticName>
              <ModifierSet>
                <Modifier>placeholder</Modifier>
              </ModifierSet>
              <FalsePositiveChance>0.05</FalsePositiveChance>
            </StatisticSpecification>
          </MetricSpecification>
        </MetricSpecificationSet>
        <MetricResultSet>
          <MetricResult>
            <MetricName>placeholder</MetricName>
            <AllocatedStudyArmSet>
              <AllocatedStudyArm>
                <Name>placeholder</Name>
                <MetricValue>placeholder</MetricValue>
              </AllocatedStudyArm>
            </AllocatedStudyArmSet>
          </MetricResult>
        </MetricResultSet>
      </PopulationSpecification>
      <Conclusion>Drug and Alcohol Dependence 2012;120(1-3):55-64. [doi: 10.1016/j.drugalcdep.2011.06.024]</Conclusion>
      <KeywordSet>
        <Keyword>Dace S. Svikis, PhD (Virginia Commonwealth University, MA Node), Lori Keyser-Marcus, PhD (Virginia Commonwealth University, MA Node), Maxine L. Stitzer, PhD (Johns Hopkins University School of Medicine), Traci R. Rieckmann, PhD (Oregon Health Science University, WS Node), Lauretta Safford, MSW (Virginia Commonwealth University, MA Node), Peter Loeb (Allen and Loeb Associates, San Francisco), Tim Allen (Allen and Loeb Associates, San Francisco), Carol Luna-Anderson, PhD (The Life Link, SW Node), Sudie E. Back, PhD (Medical University of South Carolina, SC Node), Judith Cohen, PhD (East Bay Community Recovery Project, WS Node), Michael A. DeBernardi, PsyD (The Life Link, SW Node), Bruce Dillard (Medical University of South Carolina, SC Node), Alyssa A. Forcehimes, PhD (University of New Mexico, SW Node), William B. Jaffee, PhD (McLean Hospital, NEC Node), Therese Killeen, PhD, APRN (Medical University of South Carolina, SC Node), Ken B. Kolodner (Epidemiology and Statistical Consulting, Baltimore, MD), Michael S. Levy, PhD (CAB Health and Recovery Services, NEC Node), Diane Pallas, PsyD (Na'Nizhoozhi Center, Inc., SW Node), Harold I. Perl, PhD (Center for the Clinical Trials Network, NIDA), Jennifer Sharpe Potter, PhD, MPH (University of Texas Health Science Center, NEC Node), Scott E. Provost, MSW, MM (McLean Hospital, NEC Node), Karen Reese, MA, CAC-AD (Man Alive, Inc., MA Node), Royce Sampson, MSN, APRN-BC (Medical University of South Carolina, SC Node), Allison Sepulveda (Virginia Commonwealth University, MA Node), Ned Snead (Chesterfield Community Services Board, MA Node), Conrad J. Wong, PhD (Eli Lily and Company, Greenwood, IN), Joan E. Zweben, PhD (East Bay Community Recovery Project, WS Node).</Keyword>
      </KeywordSet>
    </Abstract>
  </ProjectDescription>
</Project>
