<?xml version="1.0"?>
<Project>
  <ProjectTitle>Comments?</ProjectTitle>
  <CitationSet>
    <Citation>CTN-0031 Primary Outcomes</Citation>
  </CitationSet>
  <AuthorSet>
    <Name>Stimulant Abuser Groups to Engage in 12-Step</Name>
    <DegreeSet/>
    <AffiliationSet>
      <Affiliation>STAGE-12): A Multisite Trial in the National Institute on Drug Abuse Clinical Trials Network.</Affiliation>
    </AffiliationSet>
  </AuthorSet>
  <ProjectDescription>
    <Abstract>
      <AbstractText>Journal of Substance Abuse Treatment 2013;44(1):103-114. [doi: 10.1016/j.jsat.2012.04.004]</AbstractText>
      <PopulationSpecification>
        <Enrollment>
          <CriterionSet>
            <Criterion>
              <CriterionType>placeholder</CriterionType>
              <CriterionSpecification>placeholder</CriterionSpecification>
            </Criterion>
          </CriterionSet>
        </Enrollment>
        <Allocation>
          <AllocationPredicate>
            <AllocationPredicateFunction>
              <AllocationPredicateFunctionSignature>placeholder</AllocationPredicateFunctionSignature>
              <AllocationPredicateFunctionArgumentSet>
                <AllocationPredicateFunctionArgument>
                  <AllocationPredicateFunctionArgumentName>placeholder</AllocationPredicateFunctionArgumentName>
                  <AllocationPredicateFunctionArgumentValue>placeholder</AllocationPredicateFunctionArgumentValue>
                </AllocationPredicateFunctionArgument>
              </AllocationPredicateFunctionArgumentSet>
            </AllocationPredicateFunction>
          </AllocationPredicate>
        </Allocation>
        <AllocatedStudyArmSet>
          <AllocatedStudyArm>
            <Name>placeholder</Name>
            <InitialSize>
              <SubgroupSet>
                <Subgroup>
                  <Name>placeholder</Name>
                  <Size>placeholder</Size>
                </Subgroup>
              </SubgroupSet>
            </InitialSize>
            <InterventionSet>
              <Intervention>placeholder</Intervention>
            </InterventionSet>
            <MetricResultSet>
              <MetricResult/>
            </MetricResultSet>
          </AllocatedStudyArm>
        </AllocatedStudyArmSet>
        <PlannedActionSet>
          <PlannedAction>
            <Name>placeholder</Name>
            <IntendedTargetPopulation>placeholder</IntendedTargetPopulation>
            <PlannedActionSpecification>
              <TypeOfAction>placeholder</TypeOfAction>
              <TypeSpecificFields/>
            </PlannedActionSpecification>
          </PlannedAction>
        </PlannedActionSet>
        <MetricSpecificationSet>
          <MetricSpecification>
            <Name>placeholder</Name>
            <Measurement>
              <MeasurementName>placeholder</MeasurementName>
              <MeasurementUnits>placeholder</MeasurementUnits>
            </Measurement>
            <IntendedTargetPopulationSet>
              <IntendedTargetPopulation>
                <Name>placeholder</Name>
                <Value>placeholder</Value>
              </IntendedTargetPopulation>
            </IntendedTargetPopulationSet>
            <StatisticSpecification>
              <StatisticName>placeholder</StatisticName>
              <ModifierSet>
                <Modifier>placeholder</Modifier>
              </ModifierSet>
              <FalsePositiveChance>0.05</FalsePositiveChance>
            </StatisticSpecification>
          </MetricSpecification>
        </MetricSpecificationSet>
        <MetricResultSet>
          <MetricResult>
            <MetricName>placeholder</MetricName>
            <AllocatedStudyArmSet>
              <AllocatedStudyArm>
                <Name>placeholder</Name>
                <MetricValue>placeholder</MetricValue>
              </AllocatedStudyArm>
            </AllocatedStudyArmSet>
          </MetricResult>
        </MetricResultSet>
      </PopulationSpecification>
      <Conclusion>Dennis M. Donovan, PhD (Alcohol Drug Abuse Institute, UW, PN Node), Dennis C. Daley, PhD (University of Pittsburgh Medical Center, ATS Node), Gregory S. Brigham, PhD (Maryhaven, Inc., OV Node), Candace C. Hodgkins, PhD, LMHC (Gateway Community Services, Inc., FNA Node), Harold I. Perl, PhD (National Institute on Drug Abuse (NIDA)), Sharon B. Garrett (Alcohol Drug Abuse Institute, UW, PN Node), Suzanne R. Doyle, PhD (Alcohol Drug Abuse Institute, UW, PN Node), Anthony S. Floyd, PhD (Alcohol Drug Abuse Institute, UW, PN Node), Patricia C. Knox, PhD (Recovery Centers of King County, PN Node), Christopher Botero (ChangePoint, Inc., WS Node), Thomas M. Kelly, PhD (Western Psychiatric Institute and Clinica, ATS Node), Therese K. Killeen,PhD, APRN (Medical University of South Carolina, SC Node), Carole Hayes (Alcohol Drug Abuse Institute, UW, PN Node), Nicole Kau'iBaumhofer (Hina Mauka, PR Node), Cindy Seamans, PhD, LPC (Nexus Recovery Center, Inc., TX Node), Lucy Zammarelli (Willamette Family Treatment Services, WS Node).</Conclusion>
      <KeywordSet>
        <Keyword>This is the primary outcomes paper for CTN-0031. This study, National Drug Abuse Treatment Clinical Trials Network protocol CTN-0031 (" Stimulant Abuser Groups to Engage in 12-Step (STAGE-12)"), evaluated the effectiveness of an 8-week combined group plus individual 12-step facilitative intervention on stimulant drug use and 12-step meeting attendance and service. Using a multisite randomized controlled trial, with assessments at baseline, mid-treatment, end of treatment, and 3- and 6-month post-randomization follow-ups (FUs), individuals with stimulant use disorders (n=471) were randomly assigned to treatment as usual (TAU) or TAU into which the Stimulant Abuser Groups to Engage in 12-Step (STAGE-12) intervention was integrated. The STAGE-12 intervention used group sessions focused on increasing acceptance of 12-step principles, as well as individual sessions incorporating an intensive referral procedure connecting participants to 12-step volunteers. Compared with TAU, STAGE-12 participants had significantly greater odds of self-reported stimulant abstinence during the active 8-week treatment phase; however, among those who had not achieved abstinence during this period, STAGE-12 participants had more days of use. STAGE-12 participants had lower Addiction Severity Index Drug Composite scores at and a significant reduction from baseline to the 3-month FU, attended 12-step meetings on a greater number of days during the early phase of active treatment, engaged in more other types of 12-step activities throughout the active treatment phase and the entire FU period, and had more days of self-reported service at meetings from mid-treatment through the 6-month FU.</Keyword>
      </KeywordSet>
    </Abstract>
  </ProjectDescription>
</Project>
