<?xml version="1.0"?>
<Project>
  <ProjectTitle>PubMed Central (free) Journal subscriber access CTN-0012 Primary Outcomes Health Services for HIV/AIDS, HCV, and Sexually Transmitted Infections in Substance Abuse Treatment Programs. Public Health Reports 2007;122(4):441-451. Lawrence S. Brown Jr., MD, MPH (Addiction Research and Treatment Corporation, NY Node), Steven Allan Kritz, MD (Addiction Research and Treatment Corporation, NY Node), R. Jeffrey Goldsmith, MD (Cincinnati VA/CinARC, OV Node), James A. Robinson, MEd (Nathan Kline Institute for Psychiatric Research, NY/LI Node), Donald Alderson, MS (New York State Psychiatric Institute, NY Node), John Rotrosen, MD (New York University, NY Node). This is the Primary Outcomes Article for CTN-0012. The National Drug Abuse Treatment Clinical Trials Network conducted this study, part of protocol CTN-0012, to determine the availability of and factors associated with infection-related health services in substance abuse treatment settings. In a cross-sectional descriptive design, state policies, reimbursement for providers, state level of priority, and treatment program characteristics were studied via written surveys of administrators of substance abuse treatment programs and of state health and substance abuse departments. Data from health departments and substance abuse agencies in 48 states and from 269 substance abuse treatment programs revealed that HIV/AIDS services are more frequent than hepatitis C virus or sexually transmitted infection-related services, and that nonmedical services are more frequent than medical services. While the availability of infection-related health services is associated with medical staffing patterns, addiction pharmacotherapy services, and state priorities, reimbursement was the most significant determining factor. Conclusions: These findings suggest that greater funding of these health services in substance abuse treatment settings, facilitated by supportive state policies, represents an effective response to the excess morbidity and mortality of these substance use-related infections. (Article (Peer-Reviewed), PDF, English, 2007) Keywords: Community health services | CTN primary outcomes | Health services research | Hepatitis C | HIV/AIDS | Sexually transmitted diseases | Public Health Reports (journal) Document No: 220, PMID: 17639646, PMCID: PMC1888517 Submitted by CTN Dissemination Librarians (8/3/2007). AUTHORS LINK Alderson, Donald Brown, Lawrence S. Jr. Goldsmith, R. Jeffrey Kritz, Steven Allan Robinson, James A. Rotrosen, John PROTOCOLS NIDA-CTN-0012 PARTICIPATING NODES All Nodes and CTPs were asked to participate in this study Supported by a grant from the National Institute on Drug Abuse to the University of Washington Alcohol and Drug Abuse Institute. The materials on this site have neither been created nor reviewed by NIDA. Updated 8/2009 -- http://ctndisseminationlibrary.org/display/220.htm info@ctndisseminationlibrary.org</ProjectTitle>
  <CitationSet>
    <Citation>CTN-0012 Primary Outcomes</Citation>
  </CitationSet>
  <AuthorSet>
    <Name>Health Services for HIV/AIDS</Name>
    <DegreeSet>
      <Degree>HCV</Degree>
      <Degree>and Sexually Transmitted Infections in Substance Abuse Treatment Programs.</Degree>
    </DegreeSet>
    <AffiliationSet>
      <Affiliation/>
    </AffiliationSet>
  </AuthorSet>
  <ProjectDescription>
    <Abstract>
      <AbstractText>Public Health Reports 2007;122(4):441-451.</AbstractText>
      <PopulationSpecification>
        <Enrollment>
          <CriterionSet>
            <Criterion>
              <CriterionType>placeholder</CriterionType>
              <CriterionSpecification>placeholder</CriterionSpecification>
            </Criterion>
          </CriterionSet>
        </Enrollment>
        <Allocation>
          <AllocationPredicate>
            <AllocationPredicateFunction>
              <AllocationPredicateFunctionSignature>placeholder</AllocationPredicateFunctionSignature>
              <AllocationPredicateFunctionArgumentSet>
                <AllocationPredicateFunctionArgument>
                  <AllocationPredicateFunctionArgumentName>placeholder</AllocationPredicateFunctionArgumentName>
                  <AllocationPredicateFunctionArgumentValue>placeholder</AllocationPredicateFunctionArgumentValue>
                </AllocationPredicateFunctionArgument>
              </AllocationPredicateFunctionArgumentSet>
            </AllocationPredicateFunction>
          </AllocationPredicate>
        </Allocation>
        <AllocatedStudyArmSet>
          <AllocatedStudyArm>
            <Name>placeholder</Name>
            <InitialSize>
              <SubgroupSet>
                <Subgroup>
                  <Name>placeholder</Name>
                  <Size>placeholder</Size>
                </Subgroup>
              </SubgroupSet>
            </InitialSize>
            <InterventionSet>
              <Intervention>placeholder</Intervention>
            </InterventionSet>
            <MetricResultSet>
              <MetricResult/>
            </MetricResultSet>
          </AllocatedStudyArm>
        </AllocatedStudyArmSet>
        <PlannedActionSet>
          <PlannedAction>
            <Name>placeholder</Name>
            <IntendedTargetPopulation>placeholder</IntendedTargetPopulation>
            <PlannedActionSpecification>
              <TypeOfAction>placeholder</TypeOfAction>
              <TypeSpecificFields/>
            </PlannedActionSpecification>
          </PlannedAction>
        </PlannedActionSet>
        <MetricSpecificationSet>
          <MetricSpecification>
            <Name>placeholder</Name>
            <Measurement>
              <MeasurementName>placeholder</MeasurementName>
              <MeasurementUnits>placeholder</MeasurementUnits>
            </Measurement>
            <IntendedTargetPopulationSet>
              <IntendedTargetPopulation>
                <Name>placeholder</Name>
                <Value>placeholder</Value>
              </IntendedTargetPopulation>
            </IntendedTargetPopulationSet>
            <StatisticSpecification>
              <StatisticName>placeholder</StatisticName>
              <ModifierSet>
                <Modifier>placeholder</Modifier>
              </ModifierSet>
              <FalsePositiveChance>0.05</FalsePositiveChance>
            </StatisticSpecification>
          </MetricSpecification>
        </MetricSpecificationSet>
        <MetricResultSet>
          <MetricResult>
            <MetricName>placeholder</MetricName>
            <AllocatedStudyArmSet>
              <AllocatedStudyArm>
                <Name>placeholder</Name>
                <MetricValue>placeholder</MetricValue>
              </AllocatedStudyArm>
            </AllocatedStudyArmSet>
          </MetricResult>
        </MetricResultSet>
      </PopulationSpecification>
      <Conclusion>Lawrence S. Brown Jr., MD, MPH (Addiction Research and Treatment Corporation, NY Node), Steven Allan Kritz, MD (Addiction Research and Treatment Corporation, NY Node), R. Jeffrey Goldsmith, MD (Cincinnati VA/CinARC, OV Node), James A. Robinson, MEd (Nathan Kline Institute for Psychiatric Research, NY/LI Node), Donald Alderson, MS (New York State Psychiatric Institute, NY Node), John Rotrosen, MD (New York University, NY Node).</Conclusion>
      <KeywordSet>
        <Keyword>This is the Primary Outcomes Article for CTN-0012. The National Drug Abuse Treatment Clinical Trials Network conducted this study, part of protocol CTN-0012, to determine the availability of and factors associated with infection-related health services in substance abuse treatment settings. In a cross-sectional descriptive design, state policies, reimbursement for providers, state level of priority, and treatment program characteristics were studied via written surveys of administrators of substance abuse treatment programs and of state health and substance abuse departments. Data from health departments and substance abuse agencies in 48 states and from 269 substance abuse treatment programs revealed that HIV/AIDS services are more frequent than hepatitis C virus or sexually transmitted infection-related services, and that nonmedical services are more frequent than medical services. While the availability of infection-related health services is associated with medical staffing patterns, addiction pharmacotherapy services, and state priorities, reimbursement was the most significant determining factor.</Keyword>
      </KeywordSet>
    </Abstract>
  </ProjectDescription>
</Project>
