<?xml version="1.0"?>
<Project>
  <ProjectTitle>PubMed Central (free) Journal subscriber access CTN-0013 Primary Outcomes Motivational Enhancement Therapy to Improve Treatment Utilization and Outcome in Pregnant Substance Users. Journal of Substance Abuse Treatment 2008;35(2):161-173. [doi: 10.1016/j.jsat.2007.09.006] Theresa M. Winhusen, PhD (University of Cincinnati/CinARC, OV Node), Frankie B. Kropp, MS (University of Cincinnati/CinARC, OV Node), Dean Babcock, MSW (Midtown Community Mental Health Center, OV Node), Diane Hague, MSSW (Jefferson Alcohol and Drug Abuse Center, OV Node), Sarah J. Erickson, PhD (University of New Mexico, SW Node), Connie Renz, MSW (University of North Carolina, NC Node), Leela Rau, MD (Midtown Community Mental Health Center, OV Node), Daniel F. Lewis (University of Cincinnati/CinARC, OV Node), Jeff Leimberger, PhD (Duke Clinical Research Institute, Data and Statistics Center), Eugene C. Somoza, MD, PhD (University of Cincinnati/CinARC, OV Node). This is the Primary Outcomes Article for CTN-0013. Pregnant substance users can benefit significantly from substance abuse treatment, but treatment retention can be challenging. In this CTN study (protocol CTN-0013, "Motivational Enhancement Therapy to Improve Treatment Utilization and Outcome in Pregnant Substance Users"), two hundred pregnant substance users entering outpatient substance abuse treatment at one of four treatment programs were randomized to receive either three individual sessions of Motivational Enhancement Therapy for pregnant substance users (MET-PS) or the first three individual sessions normally provided by the program. All participants were encouraged to participate in all other treatment offered by the program. Outcome measures included treatment utilization according to clinic records, qualitative urine toxicology measures, and self-report of substance use. One hundred sixty-two (81%) participants completed the 1-month active phase. Participants attended 62% of scheduled treatment on average and reported decreased substance use during the first month of treatment, with no differences between MET-PS and treatment-as-usual (TAU) participants. There was some evidence that the efficacy of MET-PS varied between sites and that MET-PS might be more beneficial than TAU in decreasing substance use in minority participants. Conclusions: MET-PS is not more effective than TAU for pregnant substance users in general but that there might be particular subgroups or treatment programs for which MET-PS might be more or less effective than TAU. (Article (Peer-Reviewed), PDF, English, 2008) Keywords: Behavior therapy | CTN primary outcomes | Gender-specific interventions | Motivational Enhancement Therapy (MET) | Motivational interviewing (MI) | Pregnant women | Retention - Treatment | Women | Journal of Substance Abuse Treatment (journal) Document No: 261, PMID: 18083322, PMCID: PMC2546520 Submitted by CTN Dissemination Librarians (3/7/2008). AUTHORS LINK Babcock, Dean Erickson, Sarah J. Hague, Diane Kropp, Frankie B. Leimberger, Jeff Lewis, Daniel F. Rau, Leela Renz, Connie Somoza, Eugene C. Winhusen, Theresa M. PROTOCOLS NIDA-CTN-0013 PARTICIPATING NODES Ohio Valley (Lead) North Carolina Southwest Supported by a grant from the National Institute on Drug Abuse to the University of Washington Alcohol and Drug Abuse Institute. The materials on this site have neither been created nor reviewed by NIDA. Updated 8/2009 -- http://ctndisseminationlibrary.org/display/261.htm info@ctndisseminationlibrary.org</ProjectTitle>
  <CitationSet>
    <Citation>CTN-0013 Primary Outcomes</Citation>
  </CitationSet>
  <AuthorSet>
    <Name>Motivational Enhancement Therapy to Improve Treatment Utilization and Outcome in Pregnant Substance Users.</Name>
    <DegreeSet/>
    <AffiliationSet>
      <Affiliation/>
    </AffiliationSet>
  </AuthorSet>
  <ProjectDescription>
    <Abstract>
      <AbstractText>Journal of Substance Abuse Treatment 2008;35(2):161-173. [doi: 10.1016/j.jsat.2007.09.006]</AbstractText>
      <PopulationSpecification>
        <Enrollment>
          <CriterionSet>
            <Criterion>
              <CriterionType>placeholder</CriterionType>
              <CriterionSpecification>placeholder</CriterionSpecification>
            </Criterion>
          </CriterionSet>
        </Enrollment>
        <Allocation>
          <AllocationPredicate>
            <AllocationPredicateFunction>
              <AllocationPredicateFunctionSignature>placeholder</AllocationPredicateFunctionSignature>
              <AllocationPredicateFunctionArgumentSet>
                <AllocationPredicateFunctionArgument>
                  <AllocationPredicateFunctionArgumentName>placeholder</AllocationPredicateFunctionArgumentName>
                  <AllocationPredicateFunctionArgumentValue>placeholder</AllocationPredicateFunctionArgumentValue>
                </AllocationPredicateFunctionArgument>
              </AllocationPredicateFunctionArgumentSet>
            </AllocationPredicateFunction>
          </AllocationPredicate>
        </Allocation>
        <AllocatedStudyArmSet>
          <AllocatedStudyArm>
            <Name>placeholder</Name>
            <InitialSize>
              <SubgroupSet>
                <Subgroup>
                  <Name>placeholder</Name>
                  <Size>placeholder</Size>
                </Subgroup>
              </SubgroupSet>
            </InitialSize>
            <InterventionSet>
              <Intervention>placeholder</Intervention>
            </InterventionSet>
            <MetricResultSet>
              <MetricResult/>
            </MetricResultSet>
          </AllocatedStudyArm>
        </AllocatedStudyArmSet>
        <PlannedActionSet>
          <PlannedAction>
            <Name>placeholder</Name>
            <IntendedTargetPopulation>placeholder</IntendedTargetPopulation>
            <PlannedActionSpecification>
              <TypeOfAction>placeholder</TypeOfAction>
              <TypeSpecificFields/>
            </PlannedActionSpecification>
          </PlannedAction>
        </PlannedActionSet>
        <MetricSpecificationSet>
          <MetricSpecification>
            <Name>placeholder</Name>
            <Measurement>
              <MeasurementName>placeholder</MeasurementName>
              <MeasurementUnits>placeholder</MeasurementUnits>
            </Measurement>
            <IntendedTargetPopulationSet>
              <IntendedTargetPopulation>
                <Name>placeholder</Name>
                <Value>placeholder</Value>
              </IntendedTargetPopulation>
            </IntendedTargetPopulationSet>
            <StatisticSpecification>
              <StatisticName>placeholder</StatisticName>
              <ModifierSet>
                <Modifier>placeholder</Modifier>
              </ModifierSet>
              <FalsePositiveChance>0.05</FalsePositiveChance>
            </StatisticSpecification>
          </MetricSpecification>
        </MetricSpecificationSet>
        <MetricResultSet>
          <MetricResult>
            <MetricName>placeholder</MetricName>
            <AllocatedStudyArmSet>
              <AllocatedStudyArm>
                <Name>placeholder</Name>
                <MetricValue>placeholder</MetricValue>
              </AllocatedStudyArm>
            </AllocatedStudyArmSet>
          </MetricResult>
        </MetricResultSet>
      </PopulationSpecification>
      <Conclusion>Theresa M. Winhusen, PhD (University of Cincinnati/CinARC, OV Node), Frankie B. Kropp, MS (University of Cincinnati/CinARC, OV Node), Dean Babcock, MSW (Midtown Community Mental Health Center, OV Node), Diane Hague, MSSW (Jefferson Alcohol and Drug Abuse Center, OV Node), Sarah J. Erickson, PhD (University of New Mexico, SW Node), Connie Renz, MSW (University of North Carolina, NC Node), Leela Rau, MD (Midtown Community Mental Health Center, OV Node), Daniel F. Lewis (University of Cincinnati/CinARC, OV Node), Jeff Leimberger, PhD (Duke Clinical Research Institute, Data and Statistics Center), Eugene C. Somoza, MD, PhD (University of Cincinnati/CinARC, OV Node).</Conclusion>
      <KeywordSet>
        <Keyword>This is the Primary Outcomes Article for CTN-0013. Pregnant substance users can benefit significantly from substance abuse treatment, but treatment retention can be challenging. In this CTN study (protocol CTN-0013, "Motivational Enhancement Therapy to Improve Treatment Utilization and Outcome in Pregnant Substance Users"), two hundred pregnant substance users entering outpatient substance abuse treatment at one of four treatment programs were randomized to receive either three individual sessions of Motivational Enhancement Therapy for pregnant substance users (MET-PS) or the first three individual sessions normally provided by the program. All participants were encouraged to participate in all other treatment offered by the program. Outcome measures included treatment utilization according to clinic records, qualitative urine toxicology measures, and self-report of substance use. One hundred sixty-two (81%) participants completed the 1-month active phase. Participants attended 62% of scheduled treatment on average and reported decreased substance use during the first month of treatment, with no differences between MET-PS and treatment-as-usual (TAU) participants. There was some evidence that the efficacy of MET-PS varied between sites and that MET-PS might be more beneficial than TAU in decreasing substance use in minority participants.</Keyword>
      </KeywordSet>
    </Abstract>
  </ProjectDescription>
</Project>
