<?xml version="1.0"?>
<Project>
  <ProjectTitle>PubMed Central (free) Journal subscriber access CTN-0015 Primary Outcomes Multisite Randomized Trial of Behavioral Interventions for Women with Co-Occurring PTSD and Substance Use Disorders. Journal of Consulting and Clinical Psychology 2009;77(4):607-619. [doi: 10.1037/a0016227] Denise Hien, PhD (Columbia School of Social Work, LI Node), Elizabeth A. Wells, PhD (Alcohol and Drug Abuse Institute, University of Washington, PN Node), Huiping Jiang, PhD (New York State Psychiatric Institute, LI Node), Lourdes Suarez-Morales, PhD (University of Miami Miller School of Medicine, FL Node), Aimee N. C. Campbell, MSW (Columbia School of Social Work, LI Node), Lisa R. Cohen, PhD (New York State Psychiatric Institute, LI Node), Gloria M. Miele, PhD (New York State Psychiatric Institute, LI Node), Therese Killeen, PhD, APRN-BC (Medical University of South Carolina, SC Node), Gregory S. Brigham, PhD (Maryhaven, Inc., OV Node), Yulei Zhang, PhD (New York State Psychiatric Institute, LI Node), Cheri Hansen (VillageSouth, Inc., FL Node), Candace Hodgkins, PhD (Gateway Community Services, FL Node), Mary A. Hatch-Maillette, PhD (Alcohol and Drug Abuse Institute, University of Washington, PN Node), Chanda Brown, PhD, LMSW (Charleston Center, SC Node), Agatha Kulaga, MSW (New York University School of Medicine, NY Node), Allison Kristman-Valente (University of Washington, PN Node), Melissa Chu, MS (Addiction Research and Treatment Corporation, NY Node), James A. Robinson, MEd (Nathan Kline Institute for Psychiatric Research, LI NY Node), David S. Liu, MD (Center for the Clinical Trials Network, NIDA), Edward V. Nunes, MD (New York State Psychiatric Institute, LI Node). This is the Primary Outcomes Article for CTN-0015. This article reports on the outcomes of CTN-0015, a protocol that compared the effectiveness of the Seeking Safety group, cognitive-behavioral treatment for substance use disorder and posttraumatic stress disorder (PTSD), to an active comparison health education group (Women's Health Education (WHE)) within the National Drug Abuse Treatment Clinical Trials Network. For the study, 353 women were randomized to received 12 sessions of Seeking Safety (M = 6.2 sessions) or WHE (M = 6.0 sessions) with follow-up assessment at 1 week, 3, 6, and 12 months posttreatment. Primary outcomes were measured by the Clinician Administered PTSD Scale (CAPS) , the PTSD Symptom Scale-Self Report (PSS-SR), and a substance use inventory (self-reported abstinence and percentage of days of use over 7 days). Intention-to-treat analysis showed large, clinically significant reductions in CAPS and PSS-SR symptoms (d = 1.94 and 1.12, respectively) but no reliable difference between conditions. Substance use outcomes were not significantly different over time between the the two treatments and at follow-up showed no significant change from baseline. Conclusions: Study results do not favor Seeking Safety over WHE as an adjunct to substance use disorder treatment for women with PTSD and reflect considerable opportunity to improve clinical outcomes in community-based treatments for these co-occurring conditions. (Article (Peer-Reviewed), PDF, English, 2009) Keywords: CTN primary outcomes | Co-occurring disorders | Gender-specific interventions | Post-traumatic stress disorder (PTSD) | Seeking Safety program | Trauma | Women | Women's Health Education program | Journal of Consulting and Clinical Psychology (journal) Document No: 371, PMID: 19634955, PMCID: PMC2795638. Submitted by CTN Dissemination Librarians, 5/21/2009 AUTHORS LINK Brigham, Gregory S. Brown, Chanda Campbell, Aimee N. C. Chu, Melissa Cohen, Lisa R. Hansen, Cheri Hatch-Maillette, Mary A. Hien, Denise Hodgkins, Candace Jiang, Huiping Killeen, Therese Kristman-Valente, Allison Kulaga, Agatha Liu, David S. Miele, Gloria M. Nunes, Edward V. Robinson, James A. Suarez-Morales, Lourdes Wells, Elizabeth A. Zhang, Yulei PROTOCOLS NIDA-CTN-0015 PARTICIPATING NODES Greater New York (formerly Long Island and New York) (Lead) Florida Node Alliance Ohio Valley Pacific Northwest Southern Consortium Supported by a grant from the National Institute on Drug Abuse to the University of Washington Alcohol and Drug Abuse Institute. The materials on this site have neither been created nor reviewed by NIDA. Updated 7/2010 -- http://ctndisseminationlibrary.org/display/371.htm info@ctndisseminationlibrary.org</ProjectTitle>
  <CitationSet>
    <Citation>CTN-0015 Primary Outcomes</Citation>
  </CitationSet>
  <AuthorSet>
    <Name>Multisite Randomized Trial of Behavioral Interventions for Women with Co-Occurring PTSD and Substance Use Disorders.</Name>
    <DegreeSet/>
    <AffiliationSet>
      <Affiliation/>
    </AffiliationSet>
  </AuthorSet>
  <ProjectDescription>
    <Abstract>
      <AbstractText>Journal of Consulting and Clinical Psychology 2009;77(4):607-619. [doi: 10.1037/a0016227]</AbstractText>
      <PopulationSpecification>
        <Enrollment>
          <CriterionSet>
            <Criterion>
              <CriterionType>placeholder</CriterionType>
              <CriterionSpecification>placeholder</CriterionSpecification>
            </Criterion>
          </CriterionSet>
        </Enrollment>
        <Allocation>
          <AllocationPredicate>
            <AllocationPredicateFunction>
              <AllocationPredicateFunctionSignature>placeholder</AllocationPredicateFunctionSignature>
              <AllocationPredicateFunctionArgumentSet>
                <AllocationPredicateFunctionArgument>
                  <AllocationPredicateFunctionArgumentName>placeholder</AllocationPredicateFunctionArgumentName>
                  <AllocationPredicateFunctionArgumentValue>placeholder</AllocationPredicateFunctionArgumentValue>
                </AllocationPredicateFunctionArgument>
              </AllocationPredicateFunctionArgumentSet>
            </AllocationPredicateFunction>
          </AllocationPredicate>
        </Allocation>
        <AllocatedStudyArmSet>
          <AllocatedStudyArm>
            <Name>placeholder</Name>
            <InitialSize>
              <SubgroupSet>
                <Subgroup>
                  <Name>placeholder</Name>
                  <Size>placeholder</Size>
                </Subgroup>
              </SubgroupSet>
            </InitialSize>
            <InterventionSet>
              <Intervention>placeholder</Intervention>
            </InterventionSet>
            <MetricResultSet>
              <MetricResult/>
            </MetricResultSet>
          </AllocatedStudyArm>
        </AllocatedStudyArmSet>
        <PlannedActionSet>
          <PlannedAction>
            <Name>placeholder</Name>
            <IntendedTargetPopulation>placeholder</IntendedTargetPopulation>
            <PlannedActionSpecification>
              <TypeOfAction>placeholder</TypeOfAction>
              <TypeSpecificFields/>
            </PlannedActionSpecification>
          </PlannedAction>
        </PlannedActionSet>
        <MetricSpecificationSet>
          <MetricSpecification>
            <Name>placeholder</Name>
            <Measurement>
              <MeasurementName>placeholder</MeasurementName>
              <MeasurementUnits>placeholder</MeasurementUnits>
            </Measurement>
            <IntendedTargetPopulationSet>
              <IntendedTargetPopulation>
                <Name>placeholder</Name>
                <Value>placeholder</Value>
              </IntendedTargetPopulation>
            </IntendedTargetPopulationSet>
            <StatisticSpecification>
              <StatisticName>placeholder</StatisticName>
              <ModifierSet>
                <Modifier>placeholder</Modifier>
              </ModifierSet>
              <FalsePositiveChance>0.05</FalsePositiveChance>
            </StatisticSpecification>
          </MetricSpecification>
        </MetricSpecificationSet>
        <MetricResultSet>
          <MetricResult>
            <MetricName>placeholder</MetricName>
            <AllocatedStudyArmSet>
              <AllocatedStudyArm>
                <Name>placeholder</Name>
                <MetricValue>placeholder</MetricValue>
              </AllocatedStudyArm>
            </AllocatedStudyArmSet>
          </MetricResult>
        </MetricResultSet>
      </PopulationSpecification>
      <Conclusion>Denise Hien, PhD (Columbia School of Social Work, LI Node), Elizabeth A. Wells, PhD (Alcohol and Drug Abuse Institute, University of Washington, PN Node), Huiping Jiang, PhD (New York State Psychiatric Institute, LI Node), Lourdes Suarez-Morales, PhD (University of Miami Miller School of Medicine, FL Node), Aimee N. C. Campbell, MSW (Columbia School of Social Work, LI Node), Lisa R. Cohen, PhD (New York State Psychiatric Institute, LI Node), Gloria M. Miele, PhD (New York State Psychiatric Institute, LI Node), Therese Killeen, PhD, APRN-BC (Medical University of South Carolina, SC Node), Gregory S. Brigham, PhD (Maryhaven, Inc., OV Node), Yulei Zhang, PhD (New York State Psychiatric Institute, LI Node), Cheri Hansen (VillageSouth, Inc., FL Node), Candace Hodgkins, PhD (Gateway Community Services, FL Node), Mary A. Hatch-Maillette, PhD (Alcohol and Drug Abuse Institute, University of Washington, PN Node), Chanda Brown, PhD, LMSW (Charleston Center, SC Node), Agatha Kulaga, MSW (New York University School of Medicine, NY Node), Allison Kristman-Valente (University of Washington, PN Node), Melissa Chu, MS (Addiction Research and Treatment Corporation, NY Node), James A. Robinson, MEd (Nathan Kline Institute for Psychiatric Research, LI NY Node), David S. Liu, MD (Center for the Clinical Trials Network, NIDA), Edward V. Nunes, MD (New York State Psychiatric Institute, LI Node).</Conclusion>
      <KeywordSet>
        <Keyword>This is the Primary Outcomes Article for CTN-0015. This article reports on the outcomes of CTN-0015, a protocol that compared the effectiveness of the Seeking Safety group, cognitive-behavioral treatment for substance use disorder and posttraumatic stress disorder (PTSD), to an active comparison health education group (Women's Health Education (WHE)) within the National Drug Abuse Treatment Clinical Trials Network. For the study, 353 women were randomized to received 12 sessions of Seeking Safety (M = 6.2 sessions) or WHE (M = 6.0 sessions) with follow-up assessment at 1 week, 3, 6, and 12 months posttreatment. Primary outcomes were measured by the Clinician Administered PTSD Scale (CAPS) , the PTSD Symptom Scale-Self Report (PSS-SR), and a substance use inventory (self-reported abstinence and percentage of days of use over 7 days). Intention-to-treat analysis showed large, clinically significant reductions in CAPS and PSS-SR symptoms (d = 1.94 and 1.12, respectively) but no reliable difference between conditions. Substance use outcomes were not significantly different over time between the the two treatments and at follow-up showed no significant change from baseline.</Keyword>
      </KeywordSet>
    </Abstract>
  </ProjectDescription>
</Project>
