<?xml version="1.0"?>
<Project>
  <ProjectTitle>PubMed Central (free) Journal subscriber access CTN-0017 Primary Outcomes Reducing HIV-Related Risk Behaviors Among Injection Drug Users in Residential Detoxification. AIDS and Behavior 2011;15(1):30-44. [doi: 10.1007/s10461-010-9751-7] Robert E. Booth, PhD (University of Colorado Health Sciences Center, RM Node), Barbara K. Campbell, PhD (Oregon Health Science University, OR/HI Node), Susan K. Mikulich-Gilbertson, PhD (University of Colorado Health Sciences Center, RM Node), Carrie Tillotson, MPH (Oregon Health Science University, OR/HI Node), Dongseok Choi, PhD (Oregon Health Science University, OR/HI Node), James A. Robinson, MEd (Nathan Kline Institute for Psychiatric Research, LI NY Nodes), Donald A. Calsyn, PhD (Alcohol Drug Abuse Institute, UW, PN Node), Raul N. Mandler, MD (Center for the Clinical Trials Network, NIDA), Lindsay M. Jenkins (Alcohol Drug Abuse Institute, UW, PN Node), Laetitia L. Thompson, PhD (University of Colorado Health Sciences Center, RM Node), Catherine L. Dempsey, PhD (University of Colorado Health Sciences Center, RM Node), Michael R. Liepman, MD (Michigan State University), Dennis McCarty, PhD (Oregon Health Science University, OR/HI Node). This is the Primary Outcomes Article for CTN-0017. Protocol CTN-0017, "HIV and HCV Prevention in Drug Treatment Settings" was a study of 632 drug injectors that tested three interventions to reduce drug and sex risk behaviors. Participants were randomized to (a) a two-session, HIV/HCV counseling and education (CE) model added to treatment as usual (TAU), (b) a one-session therapeutic alliance (TA) intervention conducted by outpatient counselors to facilitate treatment entry plus TAU, or (c) TAU. Significant reductions in drug and sex risk behaviors occurred for all three conditions over a 6-month follow-up period. CE participants reported significantly greater rates of attending an HIV testing appointment, but this was not associated with better risk reduction outcomes. Reporting treatment participation within 2 months after detoxification and self-efficacy to practice safer injection behavior predicted reductions in injection risk behaviors. Conclusions: Findings indicate that participation in detoxification was followed by significant decreases in drug injection and risk behaviors for up to six months; interventions added to standard treatment offered no improvement in risk behavior outcomes. The study supports the importance of access to detoxification for drug injectors followed by transition to continued treatment. The manuals used by this protocol are also in the CTN Dissemination Library: HIV and HCV Counseling and Education (CE) Intervention Training Manual, version 3.0 (Royer et al, 1993) Developing the Therapeutic Alliance as a Bridge to Treatment: Training Manual for the Therapeutic Alliance Intervention (Campbell, 2008) (Article (Peer-Reviewed), PDF, English, 2011) Keywords: Behavior therapy | Community health services | Cocaine | Condom use | CTN primary outcomes | Hepatitis C | HIV/AIDS | Injection drug use | Opioid dependence | Retention - Treatment | Sexual risk behavior | Sexually transmitted diseases | Stimulant abuse | Therapeutic alliance | AIDS and Behavior (journal) Document No: 515, PMID: 20652630, PMCID: PMC3023839. Submitted by CTN Dissemination Librarians, 7/28/2010.</ProjectTitle>
  <CitationSet>
    <Citation>Journal subscriber access CTN-0017 Primary Outcomes</Citation>
  </CitationSet>
  <AuthorSet>
    <Name>CTN-0017 Primary Outcomes</Name>
    <DegreeSet/>
    <AffiliationSet>
      <Affiliation/>
    </AffiliationSet>
  </AuthorSet>
  <ProjectDescription>
    <Abstract>
      <AbstractText>Reducing HIV-Related Risk Behaviors Among Injection Drug Users in Residential Detoxification.</AbstractText>
      <PopulationSpecification>
        <Enrollment>
          <CriterionSet>
            <Criterion>
              <CriterionType>placeholder</CriterionType>
              <CriterionSpecification>placeholder</CriterionSpecification>
            </Criterion>
          </CriterionSet>
        </Enrollment>
        <Allocation>
          <AllocationPredicate>
            <AllocationPredicateFunction>
              <AllocationPredicateFunctionSignature>placeholder</AllocationPredicateFunctionSignature>
              <AllocationPredicateFunctionArgumentSet>
                <AllocationPredicateFunctionArgument>
                  <AllocationPredicateFunctionArgumentName>placeholder</AllocationPredicateFunctionArgumentName>
                  <AllocationPredicateFunctionArgumentValue>placeholder</AllocationPredicateFunctionArgumentValue>
                </AllocationPredicateFunctionArgument>
              </AllocationPredicateFunctionArgumentSet>
            </AllocationPredicateFunction>
          </AllocationPredicate>
        </Allocation>
        <AllocatedStudyArmSet>
          <AllocatedStudyArm>
            <Name>placeholder</Name>
            <InitialSize>
              <SubgroupSet>
                <Subgroup>
                  <Name>placeholder</Name>
                  <Size>placeholder</Size>
                </Subgroup>
              </SubgroupSet>
            </InitialSize>
            <InterventionSet>
              <Intervention>placeholder</Intervention>
            </InterventionSet>
            <MetricResultSet>
              <MetricResult/>
            </MetricResultSet>
          </AllocatedStudyArm>
        </AllocatedStudyArmSet>
        <PlannedActionSet>
          <PlannedAction>
            <Name>placeholder</Name>
            <IntendedTargetPopulation>placeholder</IntendedTargetPopulation>
            <PlannedActionSpecification>
              <TypeOfAction>placeholder</TypeOfAction>
              <TypeSpecificFields/>
            </PlannedActionSpecification>
          </PlannedAction>
        </PlannedActionSet>
        <MetricSpecificationSet>
          <MetricSpecification>
            <Name>placeholder</Name>
            <Measurement>
              <MeasurementName>placeholder</MeasurementName>
              <MeasurementUnits>placeholder</MeasurementUnits>
            </Measurement>
            <IntendedTargetPopulationSet>
              <IntendedTargetPopulation>
                <Name>placeholder</Name>
                <Value>placeholder</Value>
              </IntendedTargetPopulation>
            </IntendedTargetPopulationSet>
            <StatisticSpecification>
              <StatisticName>placeholder</StatisticName>
              <ModifierSet>
                <Modifier>placeholder</Modifier>
              </ModifierSet>
              <FalsePositiveChance>0.05</FalsePositiveChance>
            </StatisticSpecification>
          </MetricSpecification>
        </MetricSpecificationSet>
        <MetricResultSet>
          <MetricResult>
            <MetricName>placeholder</MetricName>
            <AllocatedStudyArmSet>
              <AllocatedStudyArm>
                <Name>placeholder</Name>
                <MetricValue>placeholder</MetricValue>
              </AllocatedStudyArm>
            </AllocatedStudyArmSet>
          </MetricResult>
        </MetricResultSet>
      </PopulationSpecification>
      <Conclusion>AIDS and Behavior 2011;15(1):30-44. [doi: 10.1007/s10461-010-9751-7]</Conclusion>
      <KeywordSet>
        <Keyword>Robert E. Booth, PhD (University of Colorado Health Sciences Center, RM Node), Barbara K. Campbell, PhD (Oregon Health Science University, OR/HI Node), Susan K. Mikulich-Gilbertson, PhD (University of Colorado Health Sciences Center, RM Node), Carrie Tillotson, MPH (Oregon Health Science University, OR/HI Node), Dongseok Choi, PhD (Oregon Health Science University, OR/HI Node), James A. Robinson, MEd (Nathan Kline Institute for Psychiatric Research, LI NY Nodes), Donald A. Calsyn, PhD (Alcohol Drug Abuse Institute, UW, PN Node), Raul N. Mandler, MD (Center for the Clinical Trials Network, NIDA), Lindsay M. Jenkins (Alcohol Drug Abuse Institute, UW, PN Node), Laetitia L. Thompson, PhD (University of Colorado Health Sciences Center, RM Node), Catherine L. Dempsey, PhD (University of Colorado Health Sciences Center, RM Node), Michael R. Liepman, MD (Michigan State University), Dennis McCarty, PhD (Oregon Health Science University, OR/HI Node).</Keyword>
      </KeywordSet>
    </Abstract>
  </ProjectDescription>
</Project>
