<?xml version="1.0"?>
<Project>
  <ProjectTitle>PubMed Central (free) Journal subscriber access CTN-0019 Primary Outcomes Effectiveness of HIV/STD Sexual Risk Reduction Groups for Women in Substance Abuse Treatment Programs: Results of a NIDA Clinical Trials Network Trial. Journal of Acquired Immune Deficiency Syndromes 2008;48(5):581-589. [doi: 10.1097/QAI.0b013e31817efb6e] Susan Tross, PhD (New York State Psychiatric Institute, LI Node), Aimee N. C. Campbell, MSW (Columbia University School of Social Work, LI Node), Lisa R. Cohen, PhD (Columbia University School of Social Work, LI Node), Donald A. Calsyn, PhD (Alcohol Drug Abuse Institute, University of Washington, PN Node), Martina Pavlicova, PhD (University of Pennsylvania, DV Node), Gloria M. Miele, PhD (New York State Psychiatric Institute, LI Node), Mei-Chen Hu, PhD (Columbia University Mailman School of Public Health, NY Node), Louise F. Haynes, MSW (Lexington/Richland Alcohol and Drug Abuse Council, SC Node), Nancy Nugent, MS (Beth Israel Medical Center, NY Node), Weijin Gan, MD, PhD (New York University Child Study Center, New York University School of Medicine, NY Node), Mary A. Hatch-Maillette, PhD (Alcohol Drug Abuse Institute, University of Washington, PN Node), Raul N. Mandler, MD (National Institute on Drug Abuse, NIDA CCTN), Paul McLaughlin, MA (Hartford Dispensary, NE Node), Nabila El-Bassel, DSW (Columbia University School of Social Work, LI Node), Paul Crits-Christoph, PhD (Treatment Research Center, University of Pennsylvania School of Medicine, DV Node), Edward V. Nunes, MD (Columbia University and New York State Psychiatric Institute, LI Node). This is the Primary Outcomes Article for CTN-0019. Since drug-involved women are among the fastest growing groups with AIDS, sexual risk reduction intervention for them is a public health imperative. The objective of this study, part of protocol CTN-0019 ("Reducing HIV/STD Risk Behaviors: A Research Study for Women in Drug Abuse Treatment"), was to test the effectiveness of HIV/STD safer sex skills building (SSB) groups for women in community drug treatment. The study used a randomized trial of SSB versus standard HIV/STD Education (HE), with assessments at baseline, 3, and 6 months. Women were recruited from 12 methadone or psychosocial treatment programs in the National Drug Abuse Treatment Clinical Trials Network. Five hundred and fifteen women who had had at least one unprotected vaginal or anal sex occasion (USO) with a male partner in the past six months were randomized. In SSB, five 90-minute groups used problem solving and skills rehearsal to increase HIV/STD risk awareness, condom use, and partner negotiation skills. In HE, one 60-minute group covered HIV/STD disease, testing, treatment, and prevention information. The main outcome measured was the number of USOs at follow-up. A significant difference in mean USOs was obtained between SSB and HE over time (F = 67.2, P 0.0001). At 3 months, significant decrements were observed in both conditions. At 6 months, SSB maintained the decrease and HE returned to baseline (P 0.0377). Women in SSB had 29% fewer USOs than those in HE. Conclusions: Skills building interventions can produce ongoing sexual risk reduction in women in community drug treatment. (Article (Peer-Reviewed), PDF, English, 2008) Keywords: Community health services | Condom use | CTN primary outcomes | Gender-specific interventions | HIV/AIDS | Safer Sex Skills Building (SSSB) | Sexual risk behavior | Sexually transmitted diseases | Skills building | Women | Journal of Acquired Immune Deficiency Syndromes (journal) Document No: 293, PMID: 18645513, PMCID: PMC2723122 Submitted by CTN Dissemination Librarians, 8/25/2008. AUTHORS LINK Calsyn, Donald A. Campbell, Aimee N. C. Cohen, Lisa R. Crits-Christoph, Paul El-Bassel, Nabila Gan, Weijin Hatch-Maillette, Mary A. Haynes, Louise F. Hu, Mei-Chen Mandler, Raul N. McLaughlin, Paul Miele, Gloria M. Nugent, Nancy Nunes, Edward V. Pavlicova, Martina Tross, Susan PROTOCOLS NIDA-CTN-0019 PARTICIPATING NODES Greater New York (formerly Long Island) (Lead) Delaware Valley New England Consortium (formerly New England) North Carolina Ohio Valley Pacific Region Southern Consortium Pacific Northwest Supported by a grant from the National Institute on Drug Abuse to the University of Washington Alcohol and Drug Abuse Institute. The materials on this site have neither been created nor reviewed by NIDA. Updated 10/2009 -- http://ctndisseminationlibrary.org/display/293.htm info@ctndisseminationlibrary.org</ProjectTitle>
  <CitationSet>
    <Citation>CTN-0019 Primary Outcomes</Citation>
  </CitationSet>
  <AuthorSet>
    <Name>Effectiveness of HIV/STD Sexual Risk Reduction Groups for Women in Substance Abuse Treatment Programs: Results of a NIDA Clinical Trials Network Trial.</Name>
    <DegreeSet/>
    <AffiliationSet>
      <Affiliation/>
    </AffiliationSet>
  </AuthorSet>
  <ProjectDescription>
    <Abstract>
      <AbstractText>Journal of Acquired Immune Deficiency Syndromes 2008;48(5):581-589. [doi: 10.1097/QAI.0b013e31817efb6e]</AbstractText>
      <PopulationSpecification>
        <Enrollment>
          <CriterionSet>
            <Criterion>
              <CriterionType>placeholder</CriterionType>
              <CriterionSpecification>placeholder</CriterionSpecification>
            </Criterion>
          </CriterionSet>
        </Enrollment>
        <Allocation>
          <AllocationPredicate>
            <AllocationPredicateFunction>
              <AllocationPredicateFunctionSignature>placeholder</AllocationPredicateFunctionSignature>
              <AllocationPredicateFunctionArgumentSet>
                <AllocationPredicateFunctionArgument>
                  <AllocationPredicateFunctionArgumentName>placeholder</AllocationPredicateFunctionArgumentName>
                  <AllocationPredicateFunctionArgumentValue>placeholder</AllocationPredicateFunctionArgumentValue>
                </AllocationPredicateFunctionArgument>
              </AllocationPredicateFunctionArgumentSet>
            </AllocationPredicateFunction>
          </AllocationPredicate>
        </Allocation>
        <AllocatedStudyArmSet>
          <AllocatedStudyArm>
            <Name>placeholder</Name>
            <InitialSize>
              <SubgroupSet>
                <Subgroup>
                  <Name>placeholder</Name>
                  <Size>placeholder</Size>
                </Subgroup>
              </SubgroupSet>
            </InitialSize>
            <InterventionSet>
              <Intervention>placeholder</Intervention>
            </InterventionSet>
            <MetricResultSet>
              <MetricResult/>
            </MetricResultSet>
          </AllocatedStudyArm>
        </AllocatedStudyArmSet>
        <PlannedActionSet>
          <PlannedAction>
            <Name>placeholder</Name>
            <IntendedTargetPopulation>placeholder</IntendedTargetPopulation>
            <PlannedActionSpecification>
              <TypeOfAction>placeholder</TypeOfAction>
              <TypeSpecificFields/>
            </PlannedActionSpecification>
          </PlannedAction>
        </PlannedActionSet>
        <MetricSpecificationSet>
          <MetricSpecification>
            <Name>placeholder</Name>
            <Measurement>
              <MeasurementName>placeholder</MeasurementName>
              <MeasurementUnits>placeholder</MeasurementUnits>
            </Measurement>
            <IntendedTargetPopulationSet>
              <IntendedTargetPopulation>
                <Name>placeholder</Name>
                <Value>placeholder</Value>
              </IntendedTargetPopulation>
            </IntendedTargetPopulationSet>
            <StatisticSpecification>
              <StatisticName>placeholder</StatisticName>
              <ModifierSet>
                <Modifier>placeholder</Modifier>
              </ModifierSet>
              <FalsePositiveChance>0.05</FalsePositiveChance>
            </StatisticSpecification>
          </MetricSpecification>
        </MetricSpecificationSet>
        <MetricResultSet>
          <MetricResult>
            <MetricName>placeholder</MetricName>
            <AllocatedStudyArmSet>
              <AllocatedStudyArm>
                <Name>placeholder</Name>
                <MetricValue>placeholder</MetricValue>
              </AllocatedStudyArm>
            </AllocatedStudyArmSet>
          </MetricResult>
        </MetricResultSet>
      </PopulationSpecification>
      <Conclusion>Susan Tross, PhD (New York State Psychiatric Institute, LI Node), Aimee N. C. Campbell, MSW (Columbia University School of Social Work, LI Node), Lisa R. Cohen, PhD (Columbia University School of Social Work, LI Node), Donald A. Calsyn, PhD (Alcohol Drug Abuse Institute, University of Washington, PN Node), Martina Pavlicova, PhD (University of Pennsylvania, DV Node), Gloria M. Miele, PhD (New York State Psychiatric Institute, LI Node), Mei-Chen Hu, PhD (Columbia University Mailman School of Public Health, NY Node), Louise F. Haynes, MSW (Lexington/Richland Alcohol and Drug Abuse Council, SC Node), Nancy Nugent, MS (Beth Israel Medical Center, NY Node), Weijin Gan, MD, PhD (New York University Child Study Center, New York University School of Medicine, NY Node), Mary A. Hatch-Maillette, PhD (Alcohol Drug Abuse Institute, University of Washington, PN Node), Raul N. Mandler, MD (National Institute on Drug Abuse, NIDA CCTN), Paul McLaughlin, MA (Hartford Dispensary, NE Node), Nabila El-Bassel, DSW (Columbia University School of Social Work, LI Node), Paul Crits-Christoph, PhD (Treatment Research Center, University of Pennsylvania School of Medicine, DV Node), Edward V. Nunes, MD (Columbia University and New York State Psychiatric Institute, LI Node).</Conclusion>
      <KeywordSet>
        <Keyword>This is the Primary Outcomes Article for CTN-0019. Since drug-involved women are among the fastest growing groups with AIDS, sexual risk reduction intervention for them is a public health imperative. The objective of this study, part of protocol CTN-0019 ("Reducing HIV/STD Risk Behaviors: A Research Study for Women in Drug Abuse Treatment"), was to test the effectiveness of HIV/STD safer sex skills building (SSB) groups for women in community drug treatment. The study used a randomized trial of SSB versus standard HIV/STD Education (HE), with assessments at baseline, 3, and 6 months. Women were recruited from 12 methadone or psychosocial treatment programs in the National Drug Abuse Treatment Clinical Trials Network. Five hundred and fifteen women who had had at least one unprotected vaginal or anal sex occasion (USO) with a male partner in the past six months were randomized. In SSB, five 90-minute groups used problem solving and skills rehearsal to increase HIV/STD risk awareness, condom use, and partner negotiation skills. In HE, one 60-minute group covered HIV/STD disease, testing, treatment, and prevention information.</Keyword>
      </KeywordSet>
    </Abstract>
  </ProjectDescription>
</Project>
